我去商店里买点东西
I'm just gonna run to the store and get a few things.
等你剪完再来接你
I'll pick you up when you're done.
好
Okay.
我比较喜欢你在这儿陪我  不过没关系
I like it a little better when you stay, but all right.
嗨  谢尔顿
Hey, Sheldon.
嗨  我来找诺费奥先生为我理发
Hello. I'm here for my haircut with Mr. D'Onofrio.
真抱歉  托尼舅舅还在医院呢
I'm sorry, Uncle Tony's in the hospital.
他病得很厉害
He's pretty sick.
天啊  诺费奥先生在医院
Oh, dear, Mr. D'Onofrio's in the hospital.
我的命运为何如此多舛
Why do these things always happen to me?
我可以帮你理发
I can cut it for you.
你不是诺费奥先生
You're not Mr. D'Onofrio.
我的头发一般是诺费奥先生理的
I get my hair cut by Mr. D'Onofrio.
你信得过这家伙吗
You believe this guy?
先失陪一下
Excuse us for a second.
谢尔顿  没关系  他能行的
Sheldon, it's okay, he can do it.
他也是个理发师
He's a barber.
他不是理发师  他是理发师的外甥
He's not a barber, he's the nephew.
他就是理发界日益猖獗的
He's an example of the kind of nepotism
裙带关系的典型范例
that runs rampant in the barbering industry.
另外  诺费奥先生很清楚我喜欢什么样的发型
Besides, Mr. D'Onofrio knows exactly how I like my hair done
因为他有我在德州理发时的理发记录
because he has all my haircut records from my barber in Texas.
你在瞎扯什么啊
What are you talking about?
我刚搬来这里的时候
When I first moved here,
找新理发师这事儿很让我发愁
I was nervous about finding a new barber,
所以我妈就把我的理发记录
so my mother had all my haircut records
都寄给了诺费奥先生
sent here to Mr. D'Onofrio.
根本没有理发记录这回事
There's no such thing as haircut records.
不  肯定有的
Yes, there are.
你见过你的理发记录吗
Have you ever seen them?
没  不过我妈妈保证肯定寄过来了
No, but my mother assured me they were sent here,
我敢跟你打包票
and I'll bet you dollars to donuts
这家伙肯定没我的理发记录
that this one doesn't have them.
打扰一下
Uh, excuse me.
你能拿到我的理发记录吗
Do you have access to my haircut records?
你的什么
Your what?
托马斯·斯特恩斯·艾略特
著名美国诗人  诺贝尔文学奖得主
用T·S·艾略特的诗来说
To paraphrase T.S. Eliot,
世界就是这样告终的
this is the way the world ends--
这句改自他的作品《空心人》  原文为
"世界就是这样告终的  不是砰的一声而是一声抽泣"
不是砰的一声而是一个外甥
not with a bang but with a nephew.
谢尔顿  你都是个大人了  他也是专业人士
Sheldon, you're a grown man, he's a professional,
而且你的发型是1946年那张海报上的第三个
and your haircut is number three on that poster from 1946.
赶紧坐下
Just sit down
让他给你剪吧
and let him do it.
好吧  如果我剪完看起来个傻蛋
Fine, but if I come out of this looking like a dork,
那就全赖你
it's on you.
我家小孩今天讲了件特别有意思的事
So my kid said the funniest thing today.
算了
Nope.
如果你日后跟别人说这事
When you tell this story later,
记得用"古怪"这个词来形容
the word we usually use is "quirky."
生活大爆炸第五季第十八集
你能把帕马森干酪递给我吗
Can you pass the Parmesan cheese?
好
Sure.
你这是干嘛
What are you doing?
把我的头发从眼前吹开
I'm trying to get the hair out of my eyes.
谢尔顿  你就是晚了一天没理发而已
Sheldon, you are one day late for your haircut.
谢谢你  一句话点明了我的恶梦
Thank you for captioning my nightmare.
瞧  我收到我的随行指示信了
Lookie here, I got my travel orders.
"随行专家霍华德·沃罗威茨受命
"Payload Specialist Howard Wolowitz is requested
前往位于德州休斯顿的国家宇航局
to report to the NASA Johnson Space Center,
约翰逊太空中心
Houston, Texas,
于周日早上八点接受宇航员特训"
for astronaut training Monday 8:00 a.m."
不过这是宇航局的信  所以时间得按照军事格式来念
Yeah, but it's from NASA, so it's 0800.
可上面写的是"早上八点"
But it says "8:00 a.m."
你得按照军事格式来念"0800"
You read it as "0800."
可它前面没写有"O"啊
It doesn't have an "O" in front of it.
你知道哪句话前面有"O[哦]"吗
You know what does have an "oh" in front of it?
"哦  我的天  我现在是宇航员了"
"Oh, my God, I'm an astronaut,
"你就羡慕嫉妒恨吧"
and you're dying of jealousy."
那他们要...
So, what kind of things are they...?
你能消停会儿吗
Will you stop that?
我忍不住  感觉自己就像是个少女杀手
I can't help it, I feel like a teen heartthrob.
谢尔顿  我以前常给我哥剪头发
You know, Sheldon, I used to cut my brother's hair.
我也能帮你的
I could do it for you.
佩妮  我知道这是你的一片好心
Penny, I know you mean well,
用你们村里的手艺来帮我  不过呢
offering the skills of the hill folk, but, um,
在我们城里
here in town,
我们不用搅乳器来搅黄油
we don't churn our own butter,
我们也不用麻袋来做裙子
we don't make dresses out of gunny sacks,
我们也很确定不想让一个染黄发的丫头
and, uh, we sure as shootin' don't get our hair cut
来给自己理发
by bottle-blonde...
谢尔顿  为人要友善
Sheldon, be nice.
不好意思  有个坏小子的发型
I'm sorry, it's the bad boy attitude
就有个坏小子的脾气
that comes with this hair.
你可以试试我的理发师
You could go to my guy.
他在比弗利山庄[富人区]的著名美发沙龙
He's at Juan-Juan in Beverly Hills.
他们会给你沏茶  会给你按摩头皮
They bring you a cup of tea, they'll massage your scalp.
虽然要两百块  不过没准有时坐在你旁边的
It's about $200, but sometimes you look in the next chair
就是一位超级巨星  比如托尼·丹扎
and you see a superstar like Tony Danza.
快速提问
Quick question here:
我们真的已经把话题
Have we actually changed the conversation
从"我要去参加宇航员特训"
from "I'm going to astronaut training"
转到"谢尔顿找不到地方理发"了吗
to "Sheldon can't get a haircut"?
你看现在是谁在羡慕嫉妒恨
Now who's dying of jealousy?
"哦"  是你啊
"Oh," it's you.
* 我是牛仔 *
* I'm a cowboy *
邦·乔维的《亡命天涯》
* 骑着一匹铁马 *
* On a steel horse I ride *
* 我想要 *
* I'm wanted *
* 想要 *
* Wanted *
* 亡命天涯 *
* Dead or alive *
谢尔顿
Sheldon,
你把我们的情侣对唱之夜都给毁了
you're ruining girlfriend- boyfriend sing-along night.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
我在找理发店  我的时间不多了
I'm looking for a barber and I'm running out of time.
我的头发正以每飞秒
My hair is growing at the rate
1飞秒等于10的-15次方秒
1幺米等于10的-24次方米
4.6幺米的速度生长着
of 4.6 yoctometers per femtosecond.
你要是安静点  还能听见头发生长的声音
I mean, if you're quiet, you can hear it.
要不去"超级剪"美发沙龙呢
What about Supercuts?
我去过一次
I tried once.
那里无论男人还是女人
They do men's and women's hair
都坐在同一个房间里一块剪
in the same room at the same time.
那简直就像是带有摩丝的罪恶之城
It's like Sodom and Gomorrah with mousse.
这件事没那么严重
Well, this isn't a crisis.
何不干脆让头发长长点算了
Why don't you just let your hair grow out a little?
何不干脆让头发长长
Why don't I let my hair grow out?
那我何不干脆开始穿凉鞋
Um, why don't I start wearing Birkenstocks
并用"你喜欢不"这句话
and seeking validation of my opinions by asking
来求证我的选择
"Can you dig it?"
我不知道啊
Well, I don't know.
我是觉得你留长头发挺性感的
I think you might look sexy with long hair.
就留那种齐肩长发
The kind that flows down to your shoulders
骑马的时候还能随风飘动
and blows back while riding on a horse.
马背光溜溜  你胸光溜溜
Bareback and bare-chested.
brush my teeth  可用来指代"自慰"
我要去"刷牙"了  估计得刷一会儿
I'm gonna go brush my teeth; it might take a while.
宝贝儿
Hi, sweetie.
我想你
I miss you.
我也想你了
I miss you, too.
你第一天过得怎么样
So tell me all about your first day.
我该从哪讲起呢
Oh, wow, where do I even start?
我体验了零重力
I got to experience zero gravity.
酷  他们怎么做到的
Cool. How do they do that?
还挺简单的
It's pretty neat.
你坐进飞机
You get in this plane
然后垂直上升  历时大概二十秒左右
that goes almost straight up for, like, 20 seconds,
然后再跟要坠机一样  垂直下落
and then straight back down like it's going to crash, and
如此循环往复
they do it over and over again, you know,
吐到连胆汁都快出来了也没人管
no matter how many times you throw up.
你吐了吗
You threw up?
是啊  而且最变态的是
Yeah...and the craziest part is,
因为是零重力环境
because there's no gravity,
呕吐物就浮在空中
the throw-up kind of floats there...
呈一个球状
in a little ball,
如果你吓得大叫
and if your mouth is open
嘴巴张开的话
because you're screaming...
有时呕吐物就会再飘回你嘴里
...sometimes it just floats right back in.
天啊  到时候你就沦为大家的笑柄
Boy, does everyone laugh at you when that happens.
他们听起来好坏哦
That sounds mean.
没有
No.
其实我当时也想笑的
Yeah, I would have laughed, too,
只不过我不想让呕吐物二次飘回我的嘴里
but I didn't want the vomit to come back out.
总而言之
Anyway...
对了  你能不能帮我
Oh, could you do me a favor
连夜快递几条内裤过来
and overnight me some more underwear?
没问题  怎么了
Sure, why?
今天看了一眼那台离心机
I got a look at the centrifuge
明天我要在里面进行高速旋转训练
they're going to spin me around in tomorrow,
于是我隐约感觉到我带的内裤不够
and I have a hunch I packed a little light.
诺费奥先生
Mr. D'Onofrio?
是我  谢尔顿
It's me, Sheldon.
礼品店里没有任何和理发相关的礼物
They didn't have anything barber-themed in the gift shop,
所以我给你买了这个
so I got you this.
不知道您能不能看见他T恤上的小字
I don't know if you can read his little T-shirt.
上面写着  快点"熊"起来哦
It says, um, "Get well bear-y soon."
相信我  如果现在您稍微有点意识
Trust me, if you were even a little conscious right now,
肯定也会发笑的
you'd be laughing.
总而言之
Anyway...
有一项新的研究表明  昏迷中的人
There's new studies that show, people in comas
也能感知到身边发生的一切
are aware of everything going on around them.
所以说  如果您现在能听到我说话
With that in mind, if you can hear me,
请离开您的病床
move away from the light
跟着这把剪刀的声音走
and toward the sound of these scissors.
有什么可以帮到你吗
Can I help you?
是的
Yes.
你这里有类似理发店大围布的东西吗
Do you have something I could use as a cape?
天啊  你是不是把药给吐了
Oh, dear, did we spit out our pills,
然后从九楼[精神病科]偷溜出来
slip out of the ninth floor,
跑到这探险来了
and go on a little adventure?
不  不
Oh, no, no,
我只是来找他理发的
I'm just here to get my hair cut.
我明白了
I-I see.
你在这等一下
J-Jus-Just wait here one moment.
保安
Security!
我得跑了
I got to run.
但是不能拿着剪刀  那样太不安全了
But not with scissors -- that would be unsafe.
要是我把我的小马挪到这来
So, if I move my horsey here...
是不是就将军了  我是赢了吧
...isn't that checkmate and I win?
到底是不是我赢了
Well, is it or isn't it?
我们今天就下到这吧
You know, I think this is a good stopping point.
你第一次下象棋
Uh, it's your first real game.
有太多知识要消化了
I threw a lot of information at you.
不
Well, no,
你的国王被我困住了
I mean, your king is trapped.
他不能往这走  因为我在这摆了个灯塔[车]
He can't go here because of my lighthouse,
还有
and...
他也不能往这走  因为我在这摆了一个尖头小人[象]
he can't go here because of my pointy-head guy.
正如我说的  这个游戏很复杂
Like I said, complicated game.
那我到底赢没赢
So did I win or not?
你玩得开心吗
Did you have fun?
因为只要你玩得开心了  就算是赢了
Because if you had fun, then you are, you are a winner.
象棋就是这样
That's, that-that's what chess is all about.
-抱歉  谢尔顿  我这就挪开  -何必呢
- Sorry, Sheldon, I'll move.  - Eh, why?
我的位置  你的位置  有区别吗
My spot, your spot-- what difference does it make?
好吧  刚刚发生了什么
Okay, what just happened?
我不知道
I don't know.
一会是你的象棋技术堪比世界冠军
Between you playing chess like Bobby Fischer
一会是谢尔顿不介意你坐了他的位置
and Sheldon being okay with you in his spot,
我估计是有人穿越回去  踩死了只虫子[蝴蝶效应]
I'm guessing someone went back in time, stepped on a bug,
改变了人类的历史进程吧
and changed the course of human events.
亲爱的  你没事吧
Uh, sweetie, are you all right?
不  我有事
No, I'm not all right.
我本来六天前就该剪头发了
It's been six days since I was supposed to get a haircut
除此之外  无大事发生
and nothing horrible has happened.
不好意思  我不懂
Okay, I'm sorry, I don't understand.
莱纳德  给她解释下
Leonard, explain it to her.
那个  他疯了
Oh, uh, he's crazy.
我用了一生时间
I have spent my whole life
精心安排我每天该做什么
trying to bring order to the universe
就是想要给这个世界带来秩序
by carefully planning every moment of every day.
而我所有的努力
But all my efforts--
我的晚餐安排  我的睡衣轮换制
our dinner schedule, my pajama rotation,
我的排便情况试算表
my bowel movement spreadsheet--
现在我算明白了
it's clear now,
我一直在浪费时间
I've been wasting my time.
很好  我要把那恶心的表格从冰箱上拿下来
Good. I'm taking that disgusting chart off the fridge.
听我说  谢尔顿
You know, Sh-Sheldon,
有时未来不可预知也挺好的
sometimes it's nice not knowing what's coming.
我是说  看我和莱纳德
I mean, look at me and Leonard.
我们约会  分手  现在又试着复合
We went out, we broke up, now we're trying again.
我们也不知道未来会怎么样
We don't know what's gonna happen.
得了吧  你们会怎么样大家都心知肚明
Oh, please, everyone knows what's going to happen.
但我懂你们的意思
But I see your point.
我觉得这样对你挺好
I think this could be good for you.
也许你是该有所改变了
Maybe it's time for you to shake things up a bit.
你说的没错
You're right.
我应该接受无序的世界
I should embrace the chaos.
很好
Great.
那你先要做什么
What are you going to do first?
我不知道
I don't know.
我什么都可以做
I could do anything.
原来的规则通通丢掉
All bets are off.
出自莎士比亚
世界由我主宰
The world is my oyster.
我知道了
I got it.
我今晚要穿我星期二的睡衣
I'm going to put on my Tuesday pajamas tonight.
我得说  我有点担心他
I got to tell you, I'm a little worried about him.
如果我是你  我会更担心刚有一个
If I were you, I'd be worried that a girl
从没下过象棋的女生  让你输得落花流水这个事实
who's never played chess in her life just kicked your ass.
华仔  你怎么了
Howie, what happened to you?
我们通宵在野外进行生存训练
We did overnight survival training in the wilderness.
好玩
Big fun.
超级好玩
Big, big fun.
我本想在跟你视频之前洗把脸
I was gonna freshen up for you
但我在去洗手间的路上  晕过去了一小会儿
but I blacked out a little on the way to the bathroom.
生存训练
Survival training?
就像露营那样吗
Is that like camping?
对啊
Uh-huh.
除了没有食物和水
Except you don't have food or water,
也不像汉斯·克拉默营那样的
and they don't have a sunset Sabbath service
日出而作  日落而息
like they do at Camp Hess-Kramer.
你是在帐篷里睡吗
Do you sleep in tents?
不是
No.
我睡在一个洞里
I slept in a hole
还是我徒手挖的洞
I dug in the ground with my bare hands.
而且晚上的时候
And at some point during the night,
一只穿山甲爬了进来
an armadillo crawled in
还给了我爱的抱抱
and spooned me.
可怜的孩子
Poor baby.
但我做到了
But I did it.
我活下来了
I survived.
我不知道沙尘暴来时该往哪儿躲
I wasn't sure I was going to when the sandstorm hit.
我只能拉起高领毛衣盖着头
I just pulled my turtleneck up over my head
呆那儿等死
and waited for death.
但当我坐在那的时候
But somehow as I sat there,
裹在满是汗味的衣茧里
wrapped in a cocoon of my own neck-sweat,
我发现了人类精神的真谛
I found that primal part of the human spirit
就是要活下去
that just wants to keep on living,
无论付出什么代价
no matter what the cost.
你太勇敢了
You're so brave.
我为你自豪
I'm proud of you.
我吃了只蝴蝶
I ate a butterfly.
那只蝴蝶好小
It was so small
也很美
and...  beautiful,
但我好饿
but I was so hungry.
你在哭吗
Are you crying?
不  我觉得这不可能
No, I don't think it's possible.
我已经严重脱水了
I'm severely dehydrated.
我的尿就跟牙膏一样稠
My pee is like toothpaste.
华仔  如果你坚持不住  就回家吧
Howie, if you're not able to do this, come home.
我对你的感觉不会变的
It won't change how I feel about you.
谢了  亲爱的  但我不能放弃
Thanks, honey, but I can't quit.
不然的话  我就是一个
If I do, I'll just be a guy
有机会成为宇航员  却中途放弃的人
who had a chance to be an astronaut and gave it up.
那我能为你做什么吗
Well, is there anything I could do to help?
没有
No.
等等  再多寄点内裤来
Wait. Send more underwear.
千万别是谢尔顿在打小手鼓
Don't let this be Sheldon playing bongos.
拜托千万别是谢尔顿在打小手鼓
Please don't let this be Sheldon playing bongos.
莱纳德呀  你喜欢我的小手鼓吗
Hello, Leonard, do you like my bongos?
但我想呀  你没猜到我有小手鼓吧
Bet you didn't know that I had bongos.
谢尔顿  现在是凌晨三点
Sheldon, it's 3:00 o'clock in the morning.
凌晨三点呀
3:00 in the morning
正适合弹小手鼓呀
is a good time for bongos.
我刚在睡觉
I was sleeping!
莱纳德在睡觉  而我在打小手鼓
Leonard sleeps while I play bongos.
不  他被吵醒了
No, he doesn't.
莱纳德被吵醒了  而我在打小手鼓
Leonard no sleep while I play bongos.
小手鼓独奏
Bongo solo.
停  住手
Stop! Stop it!
住手  别敲了
Stop! Stop! Stop it!
他妈的怎么回事啊
What the hell?!
佩妮  你猜怎么着
Penny, guess what?
谢尔顿有对小手鼓
Sheldon got bongos.
为什么你会有小手鼓
Why did you get bongos?
理查德·费曼会打小手鼓
Richard Feynman played the bongos.
我就想说我也该试试
I thought I'd give that a try.
理查德·费曼是位著名物理学家
Richard Feynman was a famous physicist.
莱纳德  现在是凌晨三点
Oh, Leonard, it's 3:00 o'clock in the morning.
我才不管理查德·费曼
I don't care if Richard Feynman
是不是我屁股里住着的紫色妖精呢
was a purple leprechaun who lived in my butt.
佩妮是假设费曼是紫色妖精
Penny meant if he were a purple leprechaun.
佩妮忘记要用虚拟语气了
Penny forgot to use the subjunctive.
谢尔顿  睡觉去
Sheldon, go to bed.
你明早还有工作要做
You have work in the morning.
或许有  或许无
Maybe, maybe not.
或许明天我组个小手鼓乐队巡回演出去了
Maybe tomorrow I start a bongo band and tour the world.
不不  你等等
No, no, hang on, uh, uh,
根据《室友协议》
Roommate Agreement.
晚十点后不能唱民谣
No hootenannies,sing-a-longs,
伴唱或男声四重唱
or barbershop quartets after ten p.m.
《室友协议》
Roommate Agreement?
你开什么玩笑
Are you kidding?
我们生活在一个无序的世界
We are living in a world of chaos.
管他狗屁《室友协议》呢
Roommate Agreement.
你去哪
Where are you going?
我要跟着音乐走  喵喵
Wherever the music takes me, kitten.
我打着小手鼓呀  下着小楼梯呀
I play bongos walking down the stairs.
千万不要  边打小手鼓边下楼梯
Never play bongos walking down the stairs.
给你个惊喜
Surprise.
你在这干嘛
What are you doing here?
我是来助你度过难关的
I'm here to help you get through this.
你自己做不来的
You can't do it on your own,
你需要有人来照顾你
you need someone to take care of you.
我太爱你了
Oh, I love you so much.
我也爱你
Oh, I love you.
霍华德  洗澡水快凉了
Howard, your bath is getting cold!
别担心  一旦她睡着
Don't worry, once she falls asleep,
我会像穿山甲一样给你爱的抱抱
I'll spoon you like an armadillo.
昨晚半夜他带着小手鼓出现
He showed up in the middle of the night with his bongos.
我错误以为这是某种音乐求欢方式
I foolishly thought it was some sort of musical booty call.
可怜的家伙
Poor guy.
他一定精疲力竭了
He must have been exhausted.
谢尔顿想睡着呀  而莱纳德在打小手鼓呀
Sheldon like to sleep while Leonard play the bongo!
你这样有点过分吧
That was kind of uncalled for.
不  一点也不过分
No, it was called for.
怎么回事
What's going on?
好了  谢尔顿
All right, Sheldon,
你也该闹够了
this craziness has gone on long enough.
拜托回家去  让我给你理发吧
Please come home so I can cut your hair.
佩妮  你没受过培训
Penny, you're not trained.
你也没有执照
You're not licensed.
更重要的是  你拿不到我的理发记录
Most importantly, you don't have access to my haircut records.
好了  宝贝
All right, honey, look,
我们认识很久了  对吧
we've known each other for a long time now, right?
我曾带你去过迪斯尼乐园
I've taken you to Disneyland,
我帮你踢过欺负你的恶霸的关键部位
I kicked a bully in the nuts for you,
你病了我就给你唱《软猫猫》
I sing you "Soft Kitty" when you're sick,
甚至你有次还见过我的裸体
you've even saw me naked once.
抱歉  你说什么
I'm sorry, what?
说来话长
It was a long story.
谢尔顿  我发誓我不会乱来
Anyway, Sheldon, I promise I know what I'm doing.
求你让我帮你理发吧
Please let me cut your hair.
艾米  你认为呢
Amy, what do you think?
我愿意让她帮我修剪我身上的任何一处毛发
There's not a hair on my body I wouldn't let this woman trim.
好吧  走吧
Fine, let's go.
谢谢你让我睡在你的沙发上
Thank you for letting me sleep on your couch.
很少有女人会一直追着男人问
There's only so many times a woman can say,
"睡我床上好不好"
"How about the bed?"
谢尔顿怎么会见过你的裸体呢
What's this about Sheldon seeing you naked?
放心吧  我只看到过她的屁股和乳房
Oh, relax. It was just her bottom and her breasts.
差不多了
Almost done.
每次理完发
At the end of the haircut,
诺费奥先生都会给我讲个黄色笑话
Mr. D'Onofrio would tell me a dirty joke.
抱歉  我不会说什么黄色笑话
Sorry, I don't know any dirty jokes.
没事  反正我也从来没听懂过
That's okay, I never understood them anyway.
好了  觉得如何
Okay, what do you think?
有点好莱坞的感觉
it's a little Hollywood.
不过我觉得我会看习惯的
But I think I can pull it off.
理得不错  佩妮
Well done, Penny.
早告诉你啦
Ha, told you.
只需理一下脖子这块的头发
Okay, I'm just gonna clean up your neck a little
-你就可以走了  -好玩
- and then you are good to go. - Fun time.
抱歉  有时这剃刀弄得我好痒痒
Sorry, sometimes the clippers tickle me.
好吧
Okay.
好了  大功告成
Okay, yep, we're all done now.
只是...挺好的
It's just... it's good.
让我帮你把这块布拿下来
Let me just take that away from you.
-好了  -非常感谢
- Okay. - Thank you very much.
不客气
You are welcome.
看来我非搬不可了
Yeah, I'm gonna have to move.